Moving on to gallbladder and biliary tract, the first disorder is a congenital disorder.
This is called biliary atresia.
In biliary atresia, remember the word atretic means that you fail to form the lumen of a tube.
And so in this particular case, you fail to form the lumen of the extrahepatic biliary tree.
So it's the bile ducts that are outside of the liver.
This, of course, leads to biliary obstruction within the first three months of life.
Now, there's a range here because sometimes the patients can have a congenital failure to form this tree,
or sometimes it can be that they form the tree, but that it actually gets destroyed, for example, by infection.
Regardless, they generally present with neonatal jaundice very early in life.
This jaundice would be due to conjugated bilirubin.
That's because, of course, in the bile is conjugated bilirubin,
and so that conjugated bilirubin would leak into the blood.
Eventually, because there's going to be back pressure into the liver,
that's going to result in damage to the liver cells, and this can eventually progress to cirrhosis.
Chololithiasis refers to gallbladder stones,
and it's basically due to precipitation of cholesterol or bilirubin in the bile.
Now, the idea here is that you get either a high concentration of cholesterol
or a high concentration of bilirubin in the bile.
Remember, both cholesterol and bilirubin are components of bile,
and this high concentration results in a precipitation of either of these two components.
So the two types of stones, actually, are cholesterol stones and bilirubin stones.
Now, this would occur due to supersaturation, and that's, again, I've already discussed that,
a high concentration of one of these two components.
In addition, this could occur when there's decreased phospholipids or bile acids.
Now, recall that phospholipids and bile acids, they help to solubilize the cholesterol, for example,
and so if you lose the ability to solubilize the cholesterol,
you're going to increase the risk that cholesterol would precipitate.
One example of this would be a farm tie-in in which you think about a drug, for example, cholestyramine.
Cholestyramine is a lipid-lowering agent, and the way it works is by binding bile acids,
which then prohibits recycling of the bile acids by the ileum.
Recall that the ileum recycles bile acids and brings it back into the blood.
And so, for example, if you had cholestyramine, which would bind the bile acids and prohibit recycling,
then that would decrease the bile acids, and, of course, a decreased bile acid would increase the risk of a cholesterol stone.
And that's an important side effect of cholestyramine, which is that the patients can get cholesterol stones,
and that's particularly high yield, so I took a little diversion there.
In addition, stasis can increase the risk of formation of a stone,
and one example of this would be that when you have stasis, you have increased risk of growth of bacteria.
Bacteria can deconjugate, for example, the bilirubin,
and it's this type of deconjugated bilirubin in the bile that actually leads to the formation of bilirubin gallstones.
Cholesterol stones are the most common type of stone, especially in the West,
and they're usually radiolucent, so they don't show up on x-ray.
They can, on rare occasions, show up on x-ray, especially if there's associated calcium,
but generally speaking, they're radiolucent.
Here's a picture of cholesterol stones, and the key thing here, you can see that this is the gallbladder,
and the most important thing is that you see these yellow stones,
and that's the characteristic of cholesterol stones, that they have a yellow color.
The risk factors include age, and the average age is around 40.
Estrogen is another risk factor, and so female gender would also be an important risk factor.
Now, the reason this is a risk factor is because estrogens increase the activity of HMG-CoA reductase.
Of course, increased activity of HMG-CoA reductase would result in increased cholesterol synthesis.
Estrogens can also increase the lipoprotein receptors on the hepatocytes,
which would then increase cholesterol uptake,
and so these are the two ways by which estrogen, and hence female gender,
increases the risk for the formation of cholesterol stones.
Clofibrate can also increase the risk. This is a drug.
It's a lipid-lowering agent that increases HMG-CoA reductase activity,
hence increasing the amount of cholesterol produced,
and also decreases conversion of cholesterol to bile acids,
and so if you don't have enough bile acids, the cholesterol will be less soluble within the fluid,
and hence it could potentially precipitate.
There's an increased incidence in certain genetic subgroups.
For example, Native American ethnicity increases the risk.
Crohn's disease increases the risk,
and you're well aware of the fact that the most common location for Crohn's disease is the terminal ileum,
so when you damage the ileum, that decreases the reuptake of bile salts and bile acids,
and of course, if you don't have good reuptake of bile salts and bile acids,
those bile salts and acids are necessary for allowing cholesterol to solubilize within the bile,
and so therefore, if you have less solubilization,
you're going to have an increased risk for precipitation of cholesterol.
And finally, cirrhosis would increase the risk,
and that's because when there's cirrhosis, there's decreased production of bile salts by the hepatocytes.
So again, cholesterol would not be able to solubilize,
and hence, there would be an increased risk of precipitation.
Bilirubin stones are usually radio-opaque, so they show up on x-ray,
and the classic feature of bilirubin stone is that it would black in color.
Now, the risk factors for bilirubin stones are basically extravascular hemolysis.
Again, in extravascular hemolysis, you get a large amount of production of unconjugated bilirubin
by the reticuloendothelial system, in particular, the splenic macrophages.
Recall that the splenic macrophages, when they eat the red blood cells,
they break down the hemoglobin into hemoglobin,
and then the heme is broken down into iron and protoporphyrin.
The iron is recycled, but the protoporphyrin is converted to unconjugated bilirubin.
Once the liver conjugates it, it will throw all that extra bilirubin into the bile,
and now you've got a large amount of bilirubin in the bile,
increasing the risk for the formation of a bilirubin gallstone.
Biliary tract infection can also increase the risk for bilirubin gallstone.
Bacteria, when they're present within the biliary tract, can deconjugate the bilirubin,
and deconjugated bilirubin increases the risk for precipitation of bilirubin,
hence leading to a risk of bilirubin gallstones.
Gallstones are usually asymptomatic, and most patients walking around with gallstones don't have symptoms.
However, there are five key complications that can result from gallstones,
and I want to talk about each of these over the next few slides.
Biliary colic is when the patients present with waxing and waning right upper quadrant pain,
and this is due to the gallbladder contracting against the stone that's lodged in the cystic duct.
Here's the idea.
Here's the gallbladder here, and this would be the cystic duct here.
Now, if a stone were to get lodged in the cystic duct, the gallbladder would then press against it,
and as the gallbladder tried to squeeze against it,
that would result in a waxing and waning right upper quadrant pain called biliary colic.
And so that's one complication that can arise when patients have gallstones.
Now, the symptoms would be relieved if this stone were to pass through the entire system and go into the duodenum.
However, you could get obstruction here in the common bile duct,
and that would increase the risk for acute pancreatitis or obstructive jaundice.
And you're going to hear much more about obstructive jaundice when we reach the liver section.
Acute cholecystitis is when you get acute inflammation of the gallbladder wall.
The idea here is that you've got a stone impacted or stuck within the cystic duct.
Because this is stuck, pressure is going to build up here in the gallbladder wall.
And as pressure builds up, that's going to squeeze the blood vessels of the wall,
which is going to decrease the blood supply to the gallbladder.
Eventually, this gallbladder will become ischemic.
There will be bacterial overgrowth, and then the patients will get inflammation.
And that is called acute cholecystitis.
Acute cholecystitis will present with right upper quadrant pain that radiates to the right scapula.
That's high yield, it will radiate to the right scapula.
Of course, they'll also have fever and an elevated white blood cell count,
and nausea and vomiting.
They can also have an increased serum alkaline phosphatase,
and that's because the epithelium that lines the gallbladder and the biliary tract
contains alkaline phosphatase, and so as those cells are damaged and die,
alkaline phosphatase will be released within the blood.
And finally, there's a risk of rupture if left untreated.
As the wall becomes further damaged, it can obviously rupture.
Chronic cholecystitis is when there's chronic inflammation of the gallbladder,
due to chemical irritation, and this is from long-standing cholelithiasis.
One of the hallmarks of chronic cholecystitis is formation of Rokitansky-Ashoff sinuses.
Here's a picture of such a sinus, and notice that here is the gallbladder mucosa up here.
Now, normally, you shouldn't have the gallbladder mucosa diving down
into the smooth muscle of the gallbladder wall.
However, you can clearly see that there's these little outpouchings
of gallbladder mucosa diving down in between the smooth muscle,
and that's called a Rokitansky-Ashoff sinus,
and that's particularly high yield for examination purposes.
Now, these patients will present with vague right upper quadrant pain,
especially after eating, and porcelain gallbladder is a late complication.
The more there's chemical damage to the wall of the gallbladder,
the more you increase the risk for dystrophic calcification,
which can then result in something called a porcelain gallbladder.
Here's a picture of a porcelain gallbladder.
You can clearly see that the wall of the gallbladder has become calcified.
Again, that's called porcelain gallbladder.
The treatment, of course, would be cholecystectomy,
which is removal of the gallbladder.
You especially want to do this if porcelain gallbladder is present
because porcelain gallbladder is a risk factor
for the formation of gallbladder cancer.
Ascending cholangitis is another complication that can arise with bile stones,
and this is when you get bacterial infection of the bile ducts.
Now, the word ascending tells you a lot
because it's usually due to ascending infection
with enteric gram-negative bacteria.
So you get bacteria within the bowel that sort of walk their way up the ductal system.
Now, this is going to present a sepsis, jaundice, and abdominal pain,
and there's an increased incidence with choledochal lithiasis.
Again, the idea here is that you've got enteric gram-negative bacteria
that walk their way up the ductal system,
and as they do so, that's going to result in an ascending cholangitis.
Now, remember that the bile from the gallbladder is constantly flowing,
and as it flows, it normally washes away the bacteria
so that they can't rise up into this duct.
However, if you had, for example, choledochal lithiasis,
which would be a stone within the duct,
then, of course, there would be less flow,
and so the bacteria could work their way up here
and eventually cause an ascending cholangitis.
And that's why I stated here in your text
that there is an increased incidence with choledochal lithiasis.
Gallstone ileus is when a gallstone enters and obstructs the small bowel.
Now, the way by which this occurs is that a patient has cholecystitis
and then forms a fistula between the gallbladder and the small bowel.
Basically, the idea here is that you've got inflammation of the gallbladder wall.
This causes rupture of the gallbladder wall,
and a fistula is formed between the gallbladder wall and the duodenum.
Of course, large stones can then enter into the small bowel,
which could potentially obstruct the bowel,
and that would be called a gallstone ileus.
Gallbladder carcinoma is an adenocarcinoma,
and it arises from the glandular epithelium
that normally lines the gallbladder wall.
Now, one of the major risk factors are gallstones,
especially when a patient has a porcelain gallbladder.
Gallbladder carcinoma classically presents as cholecystitis in an elderly woman.
Now, remember that cholecystitis is basically a disease of 40-year-olds and 50-year-olds.
However, if you have a very old woman that presents with, for example,
new-onset cholecystitis, especially on a board exam,
you really want to think about gallbladder carcinoma as an important cause,
and this has a particularly poor prognosis.
Here's a picture of the gallbladder cut open,
and here you can see that there's a tumor growing on the wall,
and this tumor represents gallbladder carcinoma.
And that concludes this particular section.